בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we are starting on דף, daf, well our
דף daf is מ"ג, mem gimmel, we're starting on מ"ב עמוד ב'.
mem beis amud beis. Okay, all right, so starting on מ"ב עמוד
ב' mem beis amud beis and we start from about midway in
it where it says גלודה, gluda, right by an asterisk, beginning of
a line. You'll see like right in the middle of מ"ב עמוד
ב' mem beis amud beis it says גלודה gluda with an asterisk,
we start one word before. You may remember
that we had a ברייתא braisa that mentioned 18 טריפות treifos in
the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and our משנה mishna did
had 18, there are other lists that increase the number, so if
you're only going to be 18 what do you do with these
other lists? So the first was a list of four which was
the acronym was דסג"ר, desagar, ב' ס' ג' ר'. beis samech gimmel
reish. So the first one was ב', beis, בהמה beheima that has
its leg cut from the knee up. So we said all right
well that's debated, maybe he doesn't hold of that one. Then ס'
samech was חסרה, chasra, if one of the vertebrae of the spine,
one or two is missing. So that we actually said that actually
is definitely a טריפה. treifa. So what we did was we conflated
two separate ones, the המסס hamasess and the בית הכוסות, beis hakosos,
two of the inner stomachs, where we said if there's a hole
in it we essentially said just count that once, and then we're
going to count the one of the missing vertebrae of the spine.
So we're now going to finish up this group of four, the
ג' gimmel and the ר', reish, which are based on tannaic teachings,
and then we're going to look at another list to see why
they are not included in the 18. So we are now with
ואיכא גלודה. va'ika gluda. So again מ"ב עמוד ב', mem beis amud
beis, the line starts at the middle of the דף daf right
by there's an asterisk at the beginning of the line. Okay and
it says the word גלודה. gluda. What about גלודה? gluda? So גלודה
gluda is an animal that has been skinned alive. Okay so
that is mentioned in a משנה mishna that that is a טריפה.
treifa. So סבר לה רבי מאיר דמכשיר, savar leh Rabbi Meir demachshir,
no that's a debate of the Rabbis and רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's not a טריפה. treifa. So
that's why it wouldn't be included in the list of 18, this
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael would not hold of
it. Okay, ואיכא חרושה. va'ika charusa. חרושה charusa means חרושה charusa is
a word for a לולב lulav which is hardened. Right? Everybody knows
how like a לולב lulav feels after it dries out and gets
hard. It also, that's also a way of describing the hardening of
a particular organ that became very hard, you know, that lost its
moisture and became hard. So what if the lung basically gets hardened?
So if it happens naturally it's actually not a טריפה, treifa, but
if it happens בידי שמים, b'dei shamayim, if it happens through some
type of human intervention it is. So what about the חרושה? charusa?
So the גמרא, Gemara, so that everybody presumably agrees is a טריפה.
treifa. How, what are you going to do if the list only
has 18? So the גמרא Gemara says all right we're going to
have to take something else off the list. So מרה מאן תני
לה? mara man tanni lah? Who teaches that the gallbladder in our
משנה, mishna, that a gallbladder, a hole in the gallbladder is a
טריפה? treifa? That's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda.
That's, we're going to find out later that it's not universally agreed.
Not everybody agrees with that the gallbladder mentioned in our משנה, mishna,
that a hole in it makes an animal a טריפה. treifa. So
therefore if we have to open up a spot for this חרושה,
charusa, this dried out lung, what are we going to say? So
we're going to say אפיק מרה ועייל חרושה. apik mara v'ayeil charusa.
Let's take out the gallbladder from the משנה mishna since we know
that that's debated and therefore we'll make a space, you know it's
like people on a waiting list, you gotta wait for somebody so,
so we got this person off, so we got off חרושה, charusa,
we've got off the gallbladder and that made a space for the
חרושה charusa for the dried out lung and that's how our משנה
mishna could still have 18. So we've now had two things that
we feel have to be added to the משנה, mishna, this case
of the dried out lung and the case
of the vertebra, and the way we make space for them in
a list of 18 is we conflate the two inner stomachs to
count them as one and we take out the gallbladder because that
is a matter of debate. Are the גמרות Gemaras from yesterday not
up here?
Yeah I don't, yeah
because they were, no I looked downstairs and they were all there
at מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos and then they all disappeared by this
morning.
The whole set of גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
I
don't know what happened to them.
Some industrious person put them away somewhere. Maybe they, I don't know,
maybe they were put in that anteroom right before the שול shul
or something? Yeah.
Oh all right I'll check.
Yeah. I'm sorry about that. All right so now let's take a
look. Yeah.
This is sounding a lot like everybody knows there's 613 מצוות mitzvos
but
nobody can
agree on what
they are so you always have to find some way to tweak
the numbers in order to get the end result that we all
agree on. Well it is true and part of it is because
of this statement that there were 18 and you know תוספות Tosafos
says later on you know remember that statement was only said according
to. So the גמרא Gemara already implicitly said that if you don’t
agree with רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, or you basically feel that there’s
a general principle that טריפה treifa is
אינה חיה, einah chaya, and you go by our משנה, Mishnah, our
משנה Mishnah doesn’t use the number eighteen, so there’s none of the
problem. So you’re right, here it’s basically all just trying to work
within this one ברייתא brayta that says eighteen, but it doesn’t mean
that we all have to buy into this type of massaging of
the numbers. Okay, within this one ברייתא brayta we have to have
it make sense. Now, the real issue is that right now we’re
at least dealing with other Tannaitic teachings. So if there are consensus
around certain things in the תנאים, Tannaim, it is a question why
weren’t they listed in the eighteen. The bigger issue is we’re about
to teach about seven Amoraic teachings. There you could say that wasn’t
included in the original list. I’ll talk about that in a minute.
What did you want to say?
One other thing is an animal’s hide that’s been completely removed is
clearly going to
die very quickly.
Right. Right. Well, yes, how does the other...? Right. How...? I don’t
know. Well again, maybe it’s a question about whether טריפה treifa is
חיה chaya or אינה חיה.
einah chaya. Yeah, exactly.
So if טריפה treifa is חיה, chaya, then the גמרא Gemara would...
the גמרא Gemara doesn’t say, actually, but it should be pointed out,
the גמרא Gemara says that according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael it’s
a list of eighteen. It’s not because it will die; it’s possible
it will live, טריפה חיה. treifa chaya. It doesn’t raise the other
question, which is: is it possible it will die and it’s not
a טריפה? treifa? Meaning it says it’s possible that it is a
טריפה treifa and it will still
live, and there’s examples of animals that will die soon that aren’t
טריפה. treifa.
Right. Is it possible that it has an injury... no, even if
it has an injury, not just that of illness, is it possible
that as a result of injury it will die and it still
won’t be a טריפה? treifa? It’s just completely arbitrary on both sides.
So that has not been directly addressed. Okay, so let’s take a
look.
Now we have the four statements, בחג"ר: BHGR: בוקא דאטמא buka de’atma
that’s cut, its leg is cut; חסרה, chasra, if it’s missing a
part of the vertebrae from the spine;
the ג gimmel is גלודה, gluda, skinned; and the ר, reish, no
not the ר, reish, it’s the second letter חרושה charusha is a
hardened lung. So those are the four Tannaitic teachings of which we
felt we had to incorporate two, so we made space for them.
Now there’s going to be seven Amoraic teachings, שב שמעתתא, shev shmaitata,
about seven Amoraic teachings of טריפות treifas that are not mentioned in
the משנה. Mishnah. And the question is, how can we make room
for them in this list of eighteen? Now, obviously the most natural
thing would be to say, look, this list of eighteen is a
Tannaitic list, the אמוראים Amoraim added more. Okay, it’s not in the
eighteen, they were added later. But the problem is that you can
say that if there’s a general principle that טריפה אינה חיה. treifa
einah chaya. So then you could say the משנה Mishnah didn’t list
it, to some degree that was worked out by the rabbis later
and they worked out seven more. That’s if there’s a principle that
a טריפה treifa is an animal with an injury that’s not going
to live. But we’re now dealing with רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says a טריפה treifa can live and that the
list of eighteen is הלכה למשה מסיני halakha le-moshe mi-sinai and it’s
an arbitrary list. So according to that, you can’t say the אמוראים
Amoraim added to it afterwards, because on what basis did they add
to it? And it’s not part of the הלכה למשה מסיני. halakha
le-moshe mi-sinai. So that’s why we have a real problem that according
to this we have to assume that the things that the אמוראים
Amoraim added at some level were always part of the list, they
maybe hadn’t been articulated so explicitly yet, which is again a little
bit hard to believe. Which is again another one of the reasons
why the simplest thing is to assume the principle טריפה אינה חיה
treifa einah chaya and everybody’s trying to work that out. Let’s take
a look now at the seven things that the אמוראים Amoraim added.
ואיכא שב שמעתתא. ve-eika shev shmaitata. What about the seven teachings of
the אמוראים? Amoraim? And now we’re going to list all of them.
We don’t know where the גמרא’s Gemara disappeared to. Okay, דאמר רב
מתנה. de-amar Rav Masna. So here’s, count on your fingers. Number one
is רב מתנה. Rav Masna. What does he say?
האי בוקא דאטמא דשף מדוכתיה. hai buka de-itma de-shaf mi-duchtei. The בוקא
דאטמא, buka de-itma, which is basically like the upper thigh bone, a
ball and socket joint, so it got dislocated. Okay, so that’s one
thing, a dislocated upper hip
bone.
Where do you have that?
That’s a
טריפה, treifa, dislocated. Well, here you have the picture. Where this, you
see right over here at the very top of the hip here,
this ball and socket joint, so that got dislocated.
Doesn’t seem like such a...
I know, I don’t know what to say. דאמר רב חנא בר
פפא, de-amar Rav Chana bar Pappa, okay, that’s number one of the
seven. דאמר רב חנא בר פפא משמיה דרב: de-amar Rav Chana bar
Pappa mishmei de-Rav: לקתה בכוליא אחת טריפה. laksa b’kulyah achat treifa. If
even one of its kidneys has some type of a disease, which
the גמרא Gemara later says basically is like a
pus-filled
sac inside one of the kidneys. Okay, so that makes it a
טריפה, treifa, and certainly if it’s two kidneys, but... but even if
it's only one, so that's number two. Nothing, you got one. ודתנן,
u-detnan, and we taught in the משנה, Mishna, ניטל הטחול כשרה, nital
ha-techol kesheira,
so our משנה Mishna says that if the spleen is removed it's
kosher, ואמר רב אוויה משמיה דרבא, ve-amar Rav Avya mishmeih deRava,
but here we have this teaching of the אמורא, Amora, Rav Avya
in the name of Rava, לא שנו אלא ניטל, lo shanu ela
nital, ironically if the entire spleen is removed it's kosher, אבל ניקב
טריפה, aval nikav tereifa, if the spleen is there but has a
hole in it, it's a טריפה. tereifa. I have no idea why.
Presumably maybe there's a concern that it will leak certain dangerous, you
know, juices or fluids, but if the whole thing is removed it
won't be a problem. What does the spleen do anyway?
I can't remember by heart.
But who would remove it from it?
Yeah, well that's also a question, how did it get removed?
And they wouldn't know that it was removed.
Yeah, I mean that's always the question here other than like being
attacked by an animal but then you'd, yeah, I have no idea.
But the spleen is considered almost like a vestigial organ. Really? I
think it relates to the, but you can live very well without
it.
Really? So maybe it's sort of like the idea of, so maybe
it's like the idea of an appendix, right? A burst appendix is
worse than a missing appendix. So maybe it's a similar idea, right?
Absolutely worse. A spleen with a hole in it is worse than
no spleen.
Okay. Alright, so there we go.
So that we have another example where we're not dealing with, where
we have modern science. Back in those times a dislocated hip meant
the cow wasn't ever going to be able to stand up again.
Now it can be fixed by surgery.
Right, but not standing up doesn't mean it will die.
Oh yeah
if
it, then it can't graze? I mean you could feed it.
Right. Alright, so anyway, alright, so that's number three, a spleen, a
ruptured or a spleen with a hole as opposed to no spleen.
ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר שמואל, ve-amar Rabba bar bar Chana
amar Shmuel, סימנים שנשלדו ברובן טריפה, simanim she-nishledu be-ruban tereifa, if the
סימנים, simanim, our good old trachea and esophagus are, have
are basically mostly removed, meaning, meaning they're still attached in the, you
know, meat of the neck in some places but mostly they're detached
from the meat of the neck. That's also a טריפה. tereifa. That's
four. ואמר רבה בר שילא אמר רב מתנה אמר שמואל, ve-amar Rabba
bar Shila amar Rav Masana amar Shmuel,
נעקרה צלע מעיקרה טריפה. ne-ekra tsela me-ikara tereifa. We said that if
the ribs, most of the ribs are broken, but if just one
rib is removed at its very origin, meaning at the vertebra where
it connects to the spine, then even just one, not a broken
rib, but an actual uprooted rib from its origin, that makes it
a טריפה. tereifa. Okay, so that's five.
וגולגולת שנחבסה ברובה, ve-gulgoles she-nechbesa be-rubah, a head, a skull that's been
sort of beaten in. So it's not actually has a hole in
the skull, but it's been, you know, it's been pushed
in, it's been beaten in in the majority of the skull. So
that's six. ובשר החופה את רוב הכרס ברובו טריפה. u-vasar ha-chofeh es
rov ha-keres be-rubo tereifa. Now you have the meat that covers, it
literally says the meat that covers the כרס. keres. Remember the כרס
keres is the huge rumen, it's the huge stomach. So the meat
really here is referring to the muscles, the abdominal muscles. Okay, so
the abdominal muscles stretch for a good part of the underside of
the cow, but and they cover, let's see if we have a
picture,
there is a picture somewhere
here, וניקבו קרום של מוח, u-nikbu krum shel moach, which part of
the brain is that,
oh yeah, and then there's a question of which membrane and there
there's a debate,
well here for a deer, isn't this lovely, you have a deer
being suspended, you can see here the exposed part here, those are
the abdominal muscles, that's the בשר החופה את רוב הכרס. basar ha-chofeh
es rov ha-keres.
Let me see if I have anything better here.
While you're doing that I just want to tell you that a
spleen according to what I'm reading
Wikipedia or whatever, yeah,
has an important role in regard to red blood cells and the
immune system.
Okay.
So, something.
Okay. So these muscles, alright, so I don't know there's a good
picture of this. These muscles that go underneath the כרס, keres, right,
you all remember that the כרס keres here is the huge stomach
here,
right, so there are muscles that go underneath, this is בשר החופה
את רוב הכרס. basar ha-chofeh es rov ha-keres. Now it only says
the majority of the כרס keres because they don't go under the
entire כרס, keres, because some of the כרס keres is, you know,
deeper into the body and the muscles don't go underneath it. Also
those muscles extend before and behind the כרס. keres. So the point
here is is that we're only talking, we're talking about those muscles,
חופה את רוב הכרס, chofeh es rov ha-keres, the רוב rov is
because they don't cover the whole כרס, keres, but we're also talking
only about the section that runs underneath the stomach, not about the
entire length of the abdominal muscles. What about those muscles? So what
happens with those abdominal muscles? So those, if those abdominal muscles,
wait one minute, hold on, right because it doesn't say explicitly what
we're talking about, so if they are torn
ברובו, be-rubo,
if they
You
just see those muscles, right? Anyway so if those muscles are torn,
the majority of them, then it is a טרפה, treifa, the majority
of the width of them is torn. Now there you go, seven
new things not mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah. So if you assume,
if you assume that we don't have a number 18 or you
assume it's all based on a principle of whether the animal will
live or not, fine, the אמוראים Amoraim added stuff not in the
משנה. Mishnah. But if you assume there's no principle, it's just a
list that God gave משה Moshe and there's a number of 18,
so these things the אמוראים Amoraim said had to some degree already
be included in that list. How are you going to make room
for seven new items? Okay, so what we're going to do is
we're going to conflate a lot of things based on the basic
idea. So let's take...
I wonder why our משנה Mishnah wouldn't have listed them if they
really were problems.
Well,
our משנה Mishnah is not the problem. Our משנה Mishnah obviously isn't
including them. The problem is that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael doesn't list
which ones. He just says there are 18. So we assume his
18 was the list of the משנה. Mishnah. Now we're tweaking it
to get רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael 18, but רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
never listed, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael just said there are 18. Yeah,
but how do you get 18? So you start with the ones
in the משנה, Mishnah, you take out two, you add two. Now
we've got these seven, okay? Take a look Michael, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael does not say what they are.
Right, I understand, but if we're saying that you know our משנה
Mishnah has this אלו טרפות, eilu treifot, right? So אלו eilu it
means these and not others.
No, the גמרא Gemara was bothered with that. It said because at
the end you say זה הכלל, zeh haklal, so זה הכלל zeh
haklal means I'm not giving you the whole list, here's a principle,
so you can add or take away from the principle.
Yeah, but it seems like if you're trying to give a list
you try to make it as comprehensive as possible.
קתני ושייר, Katani veshayer, it's a general principle. You don't always have
a full list. You have an abbreviated list. Michael, I'm not going
to debate this, I'm not going to debate this. Let's go on.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so now we have seven
more that we have to add. So the גמרא Gemara says ניקבי
תמניא הוי. nikvei tamanya havei. The גמרא Gemara says look, count all
of the things in the משנה Mishnah that speak if there's a
hole in them they are טרפה, treifa, and you will find out
that there are eight. Okay, so rather than count every single... who
says that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael counts every one separately? Maybe it's
one category: things with holes in them, right, that counts as one,
and there are eight things that if they have holes in them,
eight organs is a טרפה. treifa. So now I've opened up seven
spots and I can bring in all of these seven. Okay, so
הוי חשבינו בחד, havei chashvinu bechad, count all eight as one, אפיק
שבע, afik sheva, so you've now taken seven off the list, ואייתי
הני שבע, veayiti hanei sheva, put these seven on the list. The
גמרא Gemara says but one minute, of that list of seven, one
of them is something that has a hole in it. So you're
not going to... okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי. ei
hachi. Oh no, I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara is going to get
to that in a minute. I'm sorry. First it has another question.
Once we're combining things to that degree, פסוקי נמי תרי הוי. psukei
nami terei havei. There are two things mentioned in the משנה Mishnah
that actually if they're cut through and through, what are they? One
is the trachea and the other is the... oh, is the spinal
cord. So if you're going to count all holes in one category,
you should count all things that are cut in one category, and
now you have opened up another spot, okay, because you have to
combine the spinal cord and the trachea. So חשבינו בחד, chashvinu bechad,
count that as one, ובצרו להו אחרינא, uvatzru lehu acharina, now you
have one less than 18, you only have 17. ועוד דרב אויה
משמיה דרבא, Veod derav Avya mishmeih deRava,
Rav Avya's teaching about a spleen with a hole in it, נמי
ניקבא הוא, nami nikva hu, that's also a hole. So now we
have to count that also part of the things of the holes,
and now we only have 16. So you've opened up so many
spots but because you're doing this very radical way of combining things,
if that's true, you not only have made spots for seven, you
actually opened up nine spots and now we only have 16, not
our 18. So what does the גמרא Gemara say? דף מ"ג עמוד
א', Daf mem gimmel amud aleph, אלא הנך תרתי דאפקינהו לא תיפוק.
ella hanech tartei deafkinhu lo teipok. All right, so remember when we
started this yesterday, we had to make room for two other things?
We had to make room for the animal with the cut leg
and the animal today we said the animal that had a heart...
I'm sorry, the animal with the removed vertebra. And how do we
make room for that? We got some other things off the list
saying that's only this opinion, that's only that opinion. So don't get
other things off the list. We used the two from yesterday that
we've made room for and include them now. And now you have
your back to your 18. Okay, great. So now we've got our
18. All right, that if you assume 18 and if you assume
it's not based on a principle of טריפה חיה treifa chaya which
could allow for the list to expand later on or continue to
be worked out. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, now that we have found
ways of more condensing the list based on the type of injury,
not the type of organ, right, that's the point about saying the
hole or the cut or so on, עולא Ulla is now going
to use this as a way of making a simpler list. Not
18, but eight. If we focus on the type of injury, not
the type of organ. Now if... talk Charlie talking about what things
this reminds you of about the תרי"ג מצוות. taryag mitzvot. So you
know it's exactly at the end of that, that comes up in
the גמרא Gemara in מכות, Makkot, right, which it starts with the
statement there are 613 מצוות, mitzvot, and then it says, you know,
came so-and-so and he boiled them down to eight, they came so-and-so
and he boiled them down to three, and he boiled it down
to... so that's also here. All right, so anyway, אמר עולא שמונה
מיני טרפות נאמרו למשה מסיני. Amar Ulla shemonah minei treifot neemru leMoshe
miSinai. There really eight types as you notice notice the word... types,
because he's not talking about the organs, he's talking about the type
of injury. Okay, so there are eight types of טרפות, trefot, what
are they? נקובה, nekuva, a hole, פסוקה, psuka, something is cut, something's
the hole is not enough, it needs to be cut, נטולה, netula,
removed, something's it's not enough to be a hole or cut, it
has to be fully removed, like the liver. Okay, spleen. No, the
spleen if it's fully removed is not a problem, it's only a
problem with a hole, right. Okay, so חסורה, chasura, something that is
lacking, meaning that let's say a piece of the of the lung
is cut away but it doesn't actually make a hole, it doesn't
go all the way through the wall, okay, but there's a piece
that's missing, קרועה, kru’ah, if it's torn, like we spoke before about
the muscles being torn, the majority of the muscles being torn, okay,
of the muscle of the abdominal muscles, other things that it's about
being torn, ו דרוסה, u’drusa, דרוסה drusa is the case of the
Mishnah when an animal, no, it sounds like crushed but it's when
the animal clawed it, okay, and there was a concern about infection
or poison, נפולה, nefula, fell off the roof, which is not about
broken bones, it's about sort of sort of like I don't know
displaced bones or something right without specifically identifying any particular internal injury,
ו שבורה, u’shvura, and things that are literally about broken bones like
most of the ribs are broken. Okay, so those are eight types
of injuries. That's nice, I mean you don't know which ones apply
to which organs, but it's a nice way of talking about the
types of injury. Okay, לאפוקי לקותא le’apokei lakuta דרב חסדא בר פפא.
deRav Chisda bar Pappa. Now the one type of thing he did
not mention was some type
of a diseased organ. So רב חסדא בר פפא Rav Chisda bar
Pappa spoke about a diseased kidney, about it having like a pus-filled
sack, and he says that's not included. Now actually that is quite
interesting, I should say, because I've been trying to sort of make
it clear what the line is between טרפה trefa and an animal
that's just going to die, like an animal that's sick or ill
or whatever. Once you say diseased, right,
then you open up the door for anything. Now it is true
that it's not talking about like a general disease like it's going
to die of pneumonia, you're talking about an organ being diseased, so
it is closer that it's about an injured organ. What? Then you
also wonder about things like let's say cancer, if it's located in,
but of course big things they have cancer though when it becomes
spread out, but anyway but here it is at least specific to
the organ. רש"י Rashi I believe says, and I'll take your point
Charlie, that the point of diseased is because we assume that when
it has this type of a pus-filled sack eventually it's going to
get a hole in it. Let me just double check that with
רש"י. Rashi. Hold on.
No, actually, I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi says the opposite. He
says no, because actually a hole in the kidney is not a
problem. So that's exactly why it's being rejected, is that a diseased
kidney is the problem and רש"י Rashi actually says don't say that
actually we can get it in the back door by calling it
something that's about to be a punctured kidney, because actually a punctured
kidney is not a problem, but a diseased kidney is, so for
רב חסדא בר פפא Rav Chisda bar Pappa it's a separate category.
So again once we introduce something like that, the exact line between
a dying animal, just generically dying, and a טרפה, trefa, a sick
or ill animal as opposed to a טרפה trefa is again not
so clear although again here this is a particular organ that is
diseased, it's not just a body-wide sickness. What did you want to
say, Charlie?
Oh pneumonia is a lung disease.
Oh it's a lung disease, that's a good point. Aha, is it—and
how does it appear?
I mean does it actually—is there something physical?
It's an infection in the lungs.
But you sort of see the lung like what? You see it,
yeah. But it—aha, I get—here the point is that it's something like
very physical, like it's like this pus-filled sort of like sack on
it, it could be something like that as opposed to just like
red
and somewhat inflamed. Right. Aha. Yeah, so it's a good question. But
it's actually just רב חסדא בר פפא Rav Chisda bar Pappa is
the first person to mention that, a diseased organ, and the גמרא
Gemara here saying that עולא Ulla rejects that. So that is a
good, so there is a question about whether that type of a
thing is included. Yes.
Can they have a heart attack?
I assume, I have no reason
to—right, you mean because—would that be
a—right, you mean because
the because the blood vessels
are constricted
but would be
visible, it would be visible if you opened them up. Some of
these injuries are visible after not from the outside of the organ
but from the inside of the organ. Right, and that's true, and
that's actually not because of a hole, it's because of actually something
additional there, but the addition is the problem. Yeah, and the גמרא,
Gemara, actually the גמרא Gemara does say by limbs, the גמרא Gemara
says that an extra limb is טרפה trefa if had that limb
been missing it would be a טרפה. trefa. The גמרא's Gemara principle
is יתירה כחסורה דמי, yeteira kechasura dami, extra like it's missing. So
if it were missing a whole leg let's say it would be
a טרפה, trefa, then if it has an extra leg it's a
טרפה trefa too. However, if it's an extra finger it's not a
טרפה trefa because a missing finger wouldn't make it a טרפה. trefa.
So that's a very strange principle the גמרא Gemara has which is
a way of also expanding the list, but so it's not always
about something lacking, so that's an interesting question too. it's also like
a question about cancer which I keep on raising. Cancer is the
presence of something. It's not a tear, it's not a rupture. But
the גמרא Gemara sometimes thinks, at least when you're dealing with a
whole limb, that extra could be just as bad as injured. So
I don't really, sometimes the exact line between diseased and טרפה treifa
is not clear, particularly in רחיש'ס Rakhish's statement about a diseased kidney.
Yes.
So I just want to understand, just bringing this back to, you
know, what happens today. So diseased, whoever the שוחט shochet is, or
the supervisors, they check to make sure that all these things are?
No, as we said way in the beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
there's questions about relying on רוב rov and חזקה, chazaka, and the
general assumption is is that these types of problems don't occur for
in the vast majority of cases.
The only thing that we basically check, the only thing that we
basically check are the lungs because lungs do have problems in lungs
are very common. The basic principle is is that you rely on
a חזקה chazaka the question is do you rely on a חזקה
chazaka or on a רוב, rov, right, if you can check and
actually know the actual facts? So the way the basic difference that
the ראשונים Rishonim developed based on the גמרא Gemara is it depends
if it's a if the likelihood of the problem is a מיעוט
המצוי, miut hamatzui, a common problem, or מיעוט שאינו מצוי. miut she'eino
matzui. If it's a non-common problem, then even if you can check,
you're not required to check. And basically uncommon problem is normally interpreted
to mean like under 5%. Under 5% we don't have to worry
about so we don't check all the organs. The only organ we
check is the lungs because their problems are greater than 5%.
So basically out of all this list there's only one problem that's
a מיעוט המצוי, miut hamatzui, which is the lungs. Right. So they
don't check for any of the others.
They don't check. If they actually see it or find it or
sometimes they know certain things, like for example a big thing came
up with cows and actually with milk of cows because they started
injecting them with certain growth hormones, and they injected them and it
made a puncture into whichever inner organ it would matter that they
made the puncture into, so therefore did they have to now say
you can't drink any milk because we assume that they all came
from cows that are טרפה. treifa. Yes, how did they get around
that? For for sure for another time, but the point is there
they knew that they had injuries. Okay, so that would be a
case, but you're right, most of the time you do not check,
it's only if you know. Yes.
This is not really for שוחט, shochet, it's for the butcher. Right.
Well, it's for the person that looks at the cow as right
after it's שחט. shechted.
Not the butcher who you who you
ship the meat to because that butcher is not do they ship
the whole carcass? Wait.
But but do they
ship the whole carcass with all of the inner organs?
No, but I think right in the slaughterhouse after you שחט, shecht,
you remove all of the inner organs, you rinse it off, I
mean you got you do some processing, right?
And that's what the שוחט shochet does?
But but but but but the קצב katzav and a שוחט shochet
are not necessarily
I understand.
I don't know who is doing it but yes, but it is
not your local butcher. Your local butcher gets it he's basically just
getting the meat. Like today. Right. So okay. All right, I don't
know.
I know they package the meat. Right.
So I don't know how the division of I get I got
it. I don't know how the division of responsibility was. But you
needed somebody there right at the time to look at when everything
when it's fresh and it could be inspected and so on. And
you're right, it might not have been the שוחט. shochet.
The butcher was quite that could be.
Okay, that that could be. I don't know. I don't know. Okay,
so let's keep on going. So that's the list of אלו eilu
by the types of things and the one thing that he explicitly
excluded was diseased. אמר חייא בר רב, Amar Chiya bar Rav, excuse
me, חייא בר רב אמר, Chiya bar Rav amar,
ח' טרפות יש בנקובה. cheit treifos yesh binquvah. There are now remember
sort of like this list we gave right a minute ago, there
are eight examples of things organs with holes in them. אם תאמר
ט', Im tomar tes, and if you'll say there are nine because
of the gallbladder, מרה, marah, no
the gallbladder that's mentioned in our משנה, mishnah, that's not universally agreed.
That's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה קתני לה. Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda katani
lah. That's only רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda. דתניא,
Detanya, נקבה הקיבה, nikvah hakeivah, if you have a hole in the
קיבה keivah which is the final stomach of the cow, the one
that's parallel to ours, נקבו הדקין, nikvu hadakin, or in the small
intestines, טרפה. treifa. רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר אף נקבה המרה, Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda omer af
nikvah hamarah, even a hole in the gallbladder. So our משנה mishnah
that mentions a hole in the gallbladder is רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda. We don't agree with that now. Do we
say about the what do we say? A torn gallbladder, removed gallbladder,
gallbladder's not a problem at all? That we don't know. But a
hole in the gallbladder is not a problem. So therefore we only
have eight not nine. Okay, now again you'll have to do the
math because our משנה mishnah had eight with gallbladder. No, excuse me
our משנה mishnah had
had nine with gallbladder. Right. So you remove the gallbladder and then
our משנה mishnah only has eight. So you can do the math.
The hole in the spleen would have made it nine, but he
doesn't necessarily agree with the teaching about the hole in the spleen.
Well, didn't we say that like there were a whole bunch of
positions and like oh this is following this opinion that opinion? So
our משנה's mishnah like four different opinions together to some to some
extent or?
Well, I mean if there are debates in תנאים, Tannaim, our משנה
mishnah has to take a position on which sides of those debates.
No, no, no, but I mean I'm you know since there's also
many of these I don't remember what we didn't we just say
like oh this position says that and what wasn't all that in
our משנה mishnah we end up getting a few different positions or
go?
First of all our משנה mishnah the
basic rearranging we were doing was not our משנה. Mishna. It was
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, who said eighteen and didn't tell us what
was on the list. So then we had to deal with all
of the material and figure out how could we get it down
to eighteen. That was basically the essence. Not within the משנה. Mishna.
The משנה Mishna says what it says. Are some of those debates?
Maybe yes, maybe no. But if you count in the משנה, Mishna,
there are actually nine cases of holes, but we've now been told
that there's eight because we're moving the gallbladder because we're being told
that that is a debate. We actually were introduced another case of
a hole in the גמרא, Gemara, which was a hole in the
spleen, but we know that that's also debated. Okay, so now he's
saying if you ignore those, those new opinions about holes, we really
only have eight. All right.
Yes, please, consider like a large lymph node and when you remove
it, you're more prone to infection.
I see, but it's not... Got it. But it's not fatal. Okay,
so אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר ר' יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי
בר יהודה. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rabbi
Yosei bar Yehuda. We rule like רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei
bar Yehuda that a hole in the, a hole in the gallbladder
is a problem. ואמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר ר' יוחנן. Va-amar
Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan. So now we're... Okay, so
that's that. So now we're done with, we've managed to rearrange things
and get eighteen for רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. We've just mentioned a
couple of debates, the most recent one being about the issue about
a question about the spleen with a hole in it, now the
question about whether the gallbladder... Okay, we've had so... those are the
overview and we've also had a list of categorizing types of injuries:
torn, holes, broken, etc., with an interesting question about disease. Now the
last thing we did was a teaching that we rule in the
name of רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef in the
name of רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. So now we're going to have
a couple of things strung together by that same tradition: רב יצחק
בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef in the name of רב יוחנן.
Rav Yochanan. So let's take a look.
ואמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר ר' יוחנן מה אהדרו ליה חבריה
לרבי יוסי בר יהודה. Va-amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan
mah ahadru leh chavrei le-Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda. So what did the,
his colleagues respond to רבי יוסי בר יהודה? Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda?
Right, רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda said a hole
in the gallbladder; his colleagues seem to feel that an injured gallbladder
was not a problem. So where did they get their evidence? By
the way, can a person live without a gallbladder?
Yeah, sure. Yeah, holy... everybody... all the time.
Do you have to take some type of a medicine to supplement
its function? No? What does it do, gallbladder? Holds bile. Oh, is
it? Yeah, yeah, it's the bile. Okay, fine. Okay, so presumably the
rabbis don't hold that an injury to a gallbladder is a problem
at all. Where did they get that evidence to respond that a
gallbladder, an injury to a gallbladder is not a problem? So, it's
a nice question. Yeah, exactly. But of course they got their answer
from the פסוקים. psukim. So where did they get this from? Okay.
ישפוך לארץ מררתי. Yishpoch la-aretz merarati. Okay, so איוב Iyov says 'My
gall, my gallbladder presumably, spills out onto the floor.' Okay, so first
of all they took that literally, not figuratively, and they said, 'Look,
so he speaks that one of his injuries was that his gallbladder
fell out of his body,' ועדיין איוב קיים, ve-adayin Iyov kayam, and
he lived! So therefore you see you can lose your gallbladder and
still live.
Gallbladder is very bitter.
Right, well that whole idea of gall, right, bitter, right, bile.
Yes. A big calamity in our community is if the chicken's gallbladder
was cut when during the שחיטה shechita of the butcher.
Oh right, because then it would... because the bile would ruin the
taste of everything. Oh that's interesting. Okay, מרה. mara. What? מרה, mara,
right, because of the bile, right. Makes sense. Ah, because of my
bitterness. You mean it doesn't even mean my... it doesn't mean my
gallbladder, it means my bile or my bitterness.
But they have that word for...
right, I understand, I understand, right and then right, the whole idea,
right, gallbladder was like the source of, right, exactly, of the emotion.
If he's שחט shachat and he sees some דם dam and then
if it's a טרפה treifa or...
No, but we'll get that when we get to כיסוי דם. kissui
dam. Okay, but anyway the גמרא Gemara is treating this literally, not
figuratively, and it says ועדיין איוב קיים, ve-adayin Iyov kayam, and he
lived. אמר להם, Amar lahem, so he must have... so he said
back to them, אין מזכירין מעשה נסים. ein mazkirin maaseh nissim. Don't
talk to me about miracles! Okay? דאי לא תימא הכי, De-i lo
tema hachi, because if you... interesting, he still doesn't even say it's
figurative, he just says it was a miracle. Because I'll show you
another פסוק pasuk by איוב: Iyov: יפלח כליותי ולא יחמול, Yefalach kilyotai
ve-lo yachmol,
'God will smite my kidneys and not have compassion.' So here, so,
you know, so there you go, and we know that it may
be questioned about an injured kidney and so on, but certainly maybe
a, you know, what do you call it, a cut kidney, etc.
So I mean there's a question. רש"י Rashi says this just means
a diseased kidney. תוספות Tosafot says that's not so clear because
because not all types of diseases are problems.
So, oh,
so
תוספות Tosafot says... I'm sorry. No, so רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
do agree that it means my kidneys would be like somehow diseased,
okay? So תוספות Tosafot just has a problem that not all diseases
are an issue, but he basically does agree that that's what the
meaning of the פסוק pasuk is. So here איוב Iyov says, 'If
my kidneys were to be, you know, would be diseased, ולא יחמול,
ve-lo yachmol, and God does not have compassion.' So you see, he
still was alive even though he had diseased kidneys! So, and we
said before that diseased kidneys, at least according to whoever it was,
who was it that spoke about the diseased kidneys?
I forget, but anyway,
where was it?
So...
yeah... Yeah, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just said it before. Right, right,
רב פפא Rav Papa, *Rav Papa*, thank you. Okay, so anyway, so
יפח לא יחמוץ ומי קחיה *Yifach lo yachmotz umi kachaya*, so how
could you live according at least to רב Rav פפא *Rav Papa*?
אלא ניסא שאני *Ella nisa shani*. It's obviously that all this was
miracles and you cannot ascribe things again, it was all figurative, it
was all miracles. And therefore you can't prove anything from this, דכתיב
*Dechtiv* because the verse says רק את נפשו שמור *Rak et nafsho
shmor*. God says at the beginning, beginning of the story to the
שטן *Satan*, he says bring out to him tons of afflictions but
keep him alive. So you see, he could make all these fatal
injuries but there was a miracle to keep him alive. So we're
reading, continuing to read the פסוקים *Pesukim* literally, but we're saying they're
not relevant. Again notice, and this is of course the whole point,
what dominates every single discussion is, can the animal live? The you
know, complete consensus, implicit assumption throughout everything is that טריפה treifa. אינה
חיה *Tereifa eina chaya*, that what determines yes or no is whether
the animal can survive or not. And also here what you see
is the assumption that טריפה *Tereifa* by אדם *Adam* is the same
as טריפה *Tereifa* by בהמה *Behemah*. That is an interesting question that
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* asks, is it really always true? And actually תוספות
Tosfos. *Tosafot* works back and forth, some גמרות *Gemarot* sound like they
are, some sound like they're not. At one point תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafot*
says maybe when the sort of you know the the organs are
the same or you know the internal you know the physical nature
of the body is the same, we can apply them. He says
there are other types of areas like he's bothered about a גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* about a hole in the membrane of the brain and
he says oh maybe that's different because humans have a thicker membrane
that protects their brain than animals. So meaning maybe we you know
it's not a universal yes or no. When they're physiologically the same
you can apply one to the other, but if they're physiologically different,
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says then not. There are other you know, some
say in general you cannot apply one to the other, that's a
question. Yes, go ahead Charlie.
Deer do not have gallbladders.
Very subtle. Just to show you can live without a gallbladder.
Okay, moving on. Okay, so that was the question about the gallbladder.
ואמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן *Ve'amar Rav Yitzchak bar
Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan*, another teaching of רב יצחק בר יוסף *Rav
Yitzchak bar Yosef* in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, הלכה
כזית Kezayit ואומר כזית kezayit *Halacha k'zayis ve'omer k'zayis*. We go like
the position of כזית *K'zayis*. What does that mean? It means again
we're always in the world of טרפות treifos. *Tereifot*. Our משנה *Mishnah*
says if the liver is removed and nothing remains, it's a טריפה
*Tereifah*. A later משנה *Mishnah* says if the liver is removed and
a כזית *K'zayis* remains, it's not a טריפה *Tereifah*. So our משנה
*Mishnah* implies that even a tiniest bit it's not a טריפה *Tereifah*,
and the later משנה *Mishnah* says you need a whole כזית *K'zayis*,
an olive-sized of the liver to not be a טריפה *Tereifah*. So
which משנה *Mishnah* do we go by? So here the teaching was
we go by the we go by the משנה *Mishnah* that says
you need a כזית *K'zayis* of the liver.
Meaning if a כזית *K'zayis* is left, it's okay.
Right, how much do you need to be left of the liver
for it to be okay? Our משנה *Mishnah* suggests any amount, a
later משנה *Mishnah* says a כזית *K'zayis*, so here we're saying like
כזית *K'zayis*. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי *Umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi*?
Did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* say that? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן *Ve'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan*, don't
we say in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* הלכה כסתם
משנה *Halacha k'stam Mishnah*? We go like a סתם משנה *Stam Mishnah*.
ותנן ניטלה הכבד ולא נשתייר ממנו כלום *Utenan nitla hakaved velo nishtayer
mimenu klum*, and our first משנה *Mishnah* which is סתם *Stam* says
if the liver is removed and nothing remains, הא נשתייר כשירה *Ha
nishtayer kesherah*, if anything remains it is okay. Now of course the
question is why is that a problem? Yes, our first סתם משנה
*Stam Mishnah* implies that if anything remains it's okay, but a later
is also a סתם משנה *Stam Mishnah*. There it says you need
a כזית *K'zayis*. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says the problem is like
this. If you have a principle הלכה כסתם משנה *Halacha k'stam Mishnah*,
then when you have two סתמים *Stamim* that contradict one another, unless
you have a good reason to go by one over the other,
you're going to have to say like you have a ספק safek.
*Safek*, you have a doubt, and you're not going to rule by
one over the other unless you have good evidence. So here if
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is ruling like the second משנה *Mishnah* of
כזית *K'zayis*, how could he rule like that if, you know, he
has two equally weighted משנה'ס *Mishnahs*? Or if you want to rule
like that tell me the reason, but you can't just like straight
rule like that. So that's how רש"י Rashi *Rashi* understands the question.
So what's the answer? So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says אמוראי נינהו
ואליבא דרבי יוחנן *Amora'ei ninhu ve'aliba d'Rabbi Yochanan*. This question of does
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* always rule by the authority of a סתם
משנה *Stam Mishnah* is a debate of אמוראים *Amoraim*. So according to
those there are אמוראים *Amoraim* that say he would rule like a
סתם משנה *Stam Mishnah* if you have two that are contradictory and
no clear evidence of one over the other, that he's going to
leave it as a ספק safek, *Safek*, he's not going to be
able to decide. But if you say רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* does
not go by the authority of a סתם משנה *Stam Mishnah* as
a general rule, so then he'll just tell you what his particular
opinion is and he doesn't have to defend why he's ruling in
side of one סתם משנה *Stam Mishnah* against another סתם משנה *Stam
Mishnah*. Okay, that's that was another statement about how do we deal
with the issue of how much of the liver has to remain.
Now we have another statement of the same tradition. ואמר רב יצחק
בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן *Ve'amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi
Yochanan*, so רב יצחק בר יוסף *Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef* in the
name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, מרה שניקבה *Marah shenikvah*, so remember
we said the gallbladder with a hole in it, at least in
our we ruled earlier, it was a debate but we ruled earlier
was a טריפה *Tereifah*. So if that although that's true, הכבד סותמה
*Hakaved sotmah*, the liver lies over the gallbladder. So if the hole
is right right between the gallbladder and the liver, so the liver
is basically keeping it sealed, okay, then כשירה *Kesherah* then it's כשר
*Kasher*. Now we're going to see in a minute the question about
what happens if some type of a skin covers up after the
hole, but רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* makes an emphasis to point out that
this was at from the very beginning of the injury it was
already essentially. not a hole because from the very time that it
got the injury, it was automatically closed up because of its location.
So that is okay. Okay, ואמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי
יוחנן *ve-amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabi Yochanan*, another teaching in
the name of רב יצחק בר יוסף *Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef* in
the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabi Yochanan*. ניקב הקורקבן והכיס שלו קיים
כשרה *nikav ha-korkevan ve-hakis shelo kayam kesherah*. If the קורקבן *korkevan*, which
is the gizzard, they used to make a joke about how a
ישיבה *yeshivah* guy, for a bird, a ישיבה *yeshivah* guy, you know,
never knew what these different sort of, you know, you know,
things were and they never had these gorgeous books in the past.
Anyway, so, so you know, there was a story, they tell the
story, I forget the details, but this is like a common story
that they tell, you know, that somebody once actually opened up a
bird and saw the קורקבן *korkevan* and said, oh, this is a
הייליגע *heilige* קורקבן *korkevan*
because you know the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* is constantly talking about the
gizzard. Who knows what it is? Anyway, so here is the open-up
sort of intestine of birds. Birds right do not have four stomachs
like cows or whatever, but they do have two stomachs. So stuff
goes from the esophagus into the crop, okay, and then it goes
down through this thing, this I don't know tube or whatever but
functions something like a stomach and digests it. And then it gets
into the gizzard, which you can see has like these thick wall
muscles, and apparently that does a lot of the grinding of the
food. Okay, and the and apparently it has two things, it has
these thick wall muscles and inside it's called the כיס *kis*. It's
got more of these like folds of the muscles inside of it
that are important for grinding the food. So those inner folds and
muscles are called the כיס *kis*, and then you have the outer
wall muscles. Okay, so how much, where does the hole go? So
let's take a look. He said it would be a problem. So
he said, ניקב הקורקבן *nikav ha-korkevan*, if the קורקבן *korkevan* has a
hole, והכיס שלו קיים *ve-hakis shelo kayam*, but these the inner muscles,
the inner membrane is still okay, to hold it in place the
membrane, then it's then it's כשרה *kesherah*, then it's okay. I just
lost my place. והכיס שלו קיים כשרה *ve-hakis shelo kayam kesherah*, it's
kosher.
איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*.
So they raise a question. ניקב הכיס והקורקבן קיים מהו *nikav hakis
ve-hakorkevan kayam mahu*? What if it's the reverse? What if this inner
membrane has a hole, but the outer walls of the קורקבן *korkevan*
are are not hole, do not have a hole? So do you
need it in both or do you just need it in the
inner membrane? So תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear. דאמר רב
נחמן *de-amar Rav Nachman*, ניקב זה בלא זה כשרה *nikav zeh belo
zeh kesherah*. Now one without the other is not a problem. You
need it the hole to go through both. Okay. Now that we're
talking about holes going through both parts of the like of the
organ, you know when it has like two double layers, we're going
to apply that same discussion to the issue of the esophagus in
a in a cow, because that also had two organs. So let's
take a look. אמר רבא Rava *amar Rava*, so אמר רבא Rava
*amar Rava* said, שני עורות יש לו לושט *shnei orot yesh lo
la-veshet*. The esophagus has two layers of skin. חיצוני אדום ופנימי לבן
*chitzon adom u-pnim lavan*. The outer one is red, the inner one
is white. Okay, fine, but they have two layers
of skin. ניקב זה בלא זה כשרה *nikav zeh belo zeh kesherah*.
If there's a hole in just one of those layers, it's not
a problem. The idea, there is a picture. Okay. The whole of
let's see so we can
see it. This big hole,
this
big thing here on the top is the trachea. Down here is
the esophagus right underneath it and you can see a little white
on the inside, right? You see it looks basically red, but you
can see a little white on the inner side. Okay. So it
has those two layers and
similarly the hole has to go through both. Okay. למה לי למימר
חיצוני אדום ופנימי לבן *lamah li le-meimar chitzon adom u-pnim lavan*? Why
do you have to point out that the outer is red and
the inner is white? I mean, yeah, I'll look at it, I'll
know. דאי חליף טרפה treifah, *de-i chalif trefah*, because if the colors
changed, if the white became red or the red became white, it's
a טרפה treifah *trefah*. Now again, that's fascinating because it changed but
no cut, no hole, no tear, no hole, right? Again, that sounds
more like something of a question of disease rather than of a
question of a hole, right? So I think רש״י Rashi's *Rashi* might
have said that it might have changed as a result of some
poison or something which gets us back to the case in the
משנה *Mishnah* about the concern of דרוסה drusa *derusah*, the concern of
poison. But anyway, so there you also have something that's not about
an injury, but if the colors reversed or changed, it's טרפה treifah
*trefah*. Okay. So now we have another thing that you need two
holes. Now we're going to have a question about both of these.
איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*. ניקבו שניהם זה שלא כנגד זה מהו *nikvu
shneihem zeh she-lo keneged zeh mahu*? Whether you're talking about the the
gizzard or whether you're talking about the about the esophagus, if you
have two holes on the inner membrane and the outer membrane, but
they're not parallel, it doesn't go a hole straight through. One is
the you know on the outer it's up here and on the
lower you know on the inner it's down here or the whatever,
reverse. But they're not they're not it's not one hole straight through.
Is that a problem or not? So what's the story? אמר מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra, משמיה דרב פפא *amar Mar Zutra mishmeih de-Rav Papa*,
בושט כשר *be-veshet kasher*, by the esophagus it's okay. בקורקבן פסול *be-korkevan
pasul*, by the gizzard it is no good. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says
the reason he assumes here that the esophagus is better is
because
why... one minute...
yeah not clear... oh
no no... רש״י Rashi, *Rashi* says the reason he assumes, I see,
the reason he assumes that in the gizzard it's no good is
because since the the food collects in the gizzard and sits around
there, there's time for it to go out of one hole and
find the. way to the other hole, whereas by the esophagus it
just comes, passes straight through, it's never going to be able to
get out of both holes. And therefore it's not as dangerous if
there's not—if they're not—if it's not a continuous hole, but it is
more dangerous in the gizzard. Okay, that was that opinion, that it's
more of a problem by the gizzard. מתקיף לה רב אשי, Rav
Ashi רב אשי Rav Ashi, asks this: אדרבא, Adaraba, the opposite. ושט,
Veshet, when it comes to the esophagus, דאכלא ביה, de'achla bei, it
eats by it, ופעיא ביה, ufa'aya bei, and cackles by it. Now
of course רש"י Rashi says one minute, it actually uses the trachea
for making sound, not esophagus, but רש"י Rashi says okay, but at
least the esophagus moves when it's making sound. So this is something
that a lot of movement occurs to it when it's breathing and
speaking. So therefore רווחא גמדי לה, revacha gamdei lei, it expands and
contracts, ופשטא לה, ufashta lei, and it, and it again, another way
of saying it
expands, וזמנין דמהנדזין בהדי הדדי, vezimnin demahandzin behadi hadadei, and sometimes they
chance upon one another. So basically he says, as the animal is
talking and eating or whatever,
the esophagus moves around, and because it's moving around, maybe the skin—the
apparently it depends if whether these two membranes are detached from one
another or they're one, but presumably they're called two, I guess they
are to some degree anyway. So it's possible the membranes will move
and that the holes will line up. I guess the real question
here is where—I mean if they're up and down, it's hard to
imagine that it's going to move like that, if maybe they're side
by side and different maybe anyway. But yes, there it's a problem
because it's possible the holes will line up. However קורקבנא דמנח ניח,
korkevana deminach nayeich, the gizzard which just sits there and nothing moves
around there, כדקאי קאי, kedekai kai, it'll stay the way it is
and it's not a problem. So he said the opposite, non-parallel holes
are a problem by the esophagus, not by the gizzard. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha breih
deRav Yosef leRav Ashi, רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רב
יוסף Rav Yosef said to רב אשי, הכי
אמרינן משמיה דמר זוטרא, hachi amrinan mishmei deMar Zutra, that's exactly what
we say in the name of מר זוטרא, דאמר משמיה דרב פפא,
de'amar mishmei deRav Papa, who says in the name of רב פפא,
כוותך, kevachach, just like you, that it's a bigger problem by the
esophagus than it is by the gizzard. Okay, so that's the end
of a series of teachings of whoever it was,
רב יצחק בר
רב יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Rav Yosef in the name of רב
יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, all around areas of טרפות. treifos. But now we're
going to move on to other אמוראית Amorait statements around טרפות. Yes?
How long does it take for a שוחט shochet to
examine—Yeah, that's a variation of Michael's question. You don't have to examine
all these things. You only examine the lungs, because only the lungs
are where there's common problems. In all these other things, the problems
are so uncommon that there's not a responsibility to check them.
So why are we talking about them?
If you happen to find them. And you did find it. Sometimes
you do.
Like where, when I
was growing up, I remember that when my mother found a chicken
that she got from the butcher, and it had red stuff in
the skin and all around the whatever, I had to take it
to the רב and ask. Now nowadays, I think in general we
tend to assume that those things will happen after the שחיטה, shechitah,
like when just they're manipulating it, they'll break a blood vessel or
whatever. But maybe not, maybe the שוחט shochet missed it, and you're
seeing all this red thing, and maybe something broke before the שחיטה.
shechitah. Yes, also the question, how does an animal lose three quarters
of its liver?
Well, that is a good question. With all of these, the question
is why we don't know how these things happen without surgery. Right,
I remember years about this. Right, yeah, I have no idea, I'd
have to see if somebody talks about it. Okay, have to do
some research on Wikipedia to see if they get emphysema. Right.
Okay, so let's—it could be
birth defects.
It could be birth defects about some of this. Yeah.
But by the time it's like a year old, you know that
it would be there.
כזית of a liver?
Alright, how can this be
a כזית of a liver?
Okay, let's keep on going.
ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava, רבא Rava. says, קרום
שעלה מחמת מכה בוושט אינו קרום. krum she'ala machamat makah beveshet eino
krum. Now this statement is about the esophagus, but according to רש"י,
Rashi this is a very general statement and a very important statement
about which was raised yesterday about injuries healing. He says if it
has a hole, he's talking specifically about the esophagus, a hole in
the esophagus and then some type of a skin, layer of skin
covers it up, grows to—scar tissue grows to cover it up, it
doesn't matter. Why does it not matter? You could have said once
it's a טרפה, treifa, it can't change its status. But רש"י Rashi
says that the basic reason is because we assume that the scar
tissue won't last and that it'll reopen. And רש"י Rashi generalizes from
this and basically says that any type of scar tissue that develops
after an after-injury wherever it might be is actually not going to
save the animal from being a טרפה treifa, if it once had
the hole. And the only time mention we made before was a
hole in the gallbladder that was opposite the liver, so from the
very beginning it was very covered up. So again, the question is,
is the issue here the sort of conceptual one that once it's
a טרפה treifa, it can't change the status, or is it the
question about whether this healing will actually, whether this scar tissue will
actually last?
Or just and even so, just for this particular thing maybe.
Right,
but— And you know when it has like these, in the lung,
does get make a lot of adhesions to the rib cage and
things around it, anyway, the question there that gets that that's central
is do we assume that the adhesion is covering up a hole?
And if it is covering up a hole, then it's a טרפה,
treifa, because even though it has the adhesion, there was once the
hole. Okay, so that's, so this issue that a later sort of
scar tissue does not help is a big issue with גלאט.
glatt. It's
like you do with the liver on top of that other.
No, no, once it started that way. The question is was there
a hole and then this came to cover it up.
What's the difference? You said that that status can't change or that
that scar tissue will deteriorate.
Well, because if it's that the scar tissue would deteriorate, in theory,
this statement was only said by the ושט, veshet, so in theory,
you could imagine that we would assess different cases differently, right? You
wouldn't globalize it. If it's based on a principle, once it's a
טרפה, end of story, then this is a globalize, more of a
globalizable state.
Well, although you could, I could just as well see that for
certain kinds of טרפה, you know, ושט veshet טרפה, that we say
it's...
Not really, not if it's a principle that once it gets that
status, it doesn't lose it, right? If it's based on it's if
it's based on the, you know, right, the health of the animal,
then yes, but then that gets more into the other category of
saying about whether the scar tissue will open up.
Since you brought up adhesion, what does an adhesion mean? Is that
another word for scar tissue?
No, because by, yes, but by the lungs, there's also there's adhesions
that are completely unrelated to scar tissue. So let's wait about when
we get to the lungs, okay? That's the whole issue of גלאט.
glatt. גלאט glatt literally means, anybody? Smooth. Smooth. It means no adhesions.
Of course, even things that we call גלאט glatt do have adhesions.
Real question is about like, what's your threshold? How, you know, how
many adhesions do you tolerate? But we'll talk about that when we
get to the lungs. Okay. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, רבא Rava says,
קודם שעלה קרום, kodem she'ala krum, excuse me, I just did that.
Okay. ואמר רבא ושט אין לו בדיקה מבחוץ אלא מבפנים. V'amar Rava
veshet ein lo bdika mibachutz ela mibifnim. You cannot check the ושט
veshet for a hole on the outside, only the inside, because remember
we said that the esophagus is red on the outside, so if
there's a hole, then maybe it's, blood is coming to fill it
up and you can't see the hole on the outside, you can
only see it on the inside where the inside is white. למאי
נפקא מינה? Lemai nafkumina? What is the נפקא מינה? nafkumina? First, you
know, you would say the נפקא מינה nafkumina is just right now
the issue of hole. So there's a whole question, a whole question
in רש''י Rashi and תוספות about whether about whether you can check
for the hole and maybe the only thing you can't check for
is לספק דרוסה. lesafek drusa. This question about ספק דרוסה, safek drusa,
remember about being punctured by the, now why is that different than
hole? Because here is apparently if, if there's certain, certain times there
are cases about animals that you don't know if, you know, a,
a lion is among your sheep, do you have to be concerned
that maybe it's actually clawed at one of them and it makes
all your sheep ספק דרוסה. safek drusa. So presumably, and again, the
assumption is is that this idea of clawing leads to some poison.
One of the results of the poison is that it turns the
organs red. So רש''י Rashi here, another רש''י Rashi says that the
question about the ability to check the esophagus is even about a
hole issue, because, you know, the blood might be filling it up
and you won't see it on the outside. Here רש''י says the
concern is about the poison issue, and since the way for detecting
poison is to see if the organs are red, that won't help
you by the ושט. veshet. You can't check it from the outside,
you can only check it from the inside.
ההוא ספק דרוסה דאתא לקמיה דרבא, Hahu safek drusa de'asa lekamei deRava,
so this question of an animal that might have been clawed came
in front of רבא. Rava, הוה קבדק ליה רבא לוושט מבראי, Havei
kabadeklei Rava leveshet mivrai, he was checking the ושט veshet from the
outside.
Okay,
where were we? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye says,
and
didn't the master say, and aren't you the one who says that
in order to check an ושט, veshet, you have to check it
from the inside? סו אפכיה רבא ובדקיה, So apchei Rava badkeiso, so
he, you know, turned it inside out and he checked it. ואשתכח
עליה תרי קורטי דמא, V'ishtachach alei trei kortei dama, and he found
two drops of blood. So again, here it sounds like it's not
about turning it red, it's, it seems that it's about blood and
about the hole, so a lot of these, it's a little unclear
these cases and there's a whole discussion in רש''י תוספות. But anyway,
he found these two drops of blood.
Wait, wait, hold on, he just said,
and רבא נמי לחדודי לאביי הוא דבעי, Rava nami lechdudi l'Abaye hu
debaei, רבא Rava, was just testing אביי. Abaye. Okay, which you don't
know if that literally was true or if the גמרא Gemara? is
just trying to protect רבא, Rava רבא, but okay. Anyway, but again,
what's interesting is, is it about blood? If it's, you know, but
דרוסה drusa is not supposed to be about holes, so the whole
things here are very, are confusing and as I said, big debates
of רש''י תוספות, whether it's about a hole and the blood, and
the blood covering up the hole, or whether it's about the effect
of דרוסה turning things red. Yes, רבקה. Rivka.
רבא was not a butcher, why would he have...
אתא לקמיה דרבא, Asa lekamei deRava, because he was a, he was
a rabbi, he was a פוסק. posek.
They said, they said, yeah, there was something happened, we think that
the animal might have been attacked, so, you know, can you check
it out to see if it's kosher or not? It happens nowadays,
right? You bring things in front of a rabbi to ask a
ספק. safek.
So it probably wasn't the שומר, shomer, it must have been the...
Right, absolutely, the producer. because the consumer would not have known that
it was a ספק דרוסה, Safek Dirusah, exactly. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Let's take a look. Okay.
אמר עולא ישב לו קוץ בוושט אין חוששין שמא הבריא. Amar Ula
yashav lo kotz bavashet ein chosheshin shema hivri. If it got a
thorn that's stuck in the inner part of its esophagus, you're not
concerned of הבריא. hivri. Now הבריא—what's hivri that mean? It means become
healthy. So רש״י's first interpretation means that we're not concerned that the
hole went all the way through and later skin covered it up,
which we said before was not good. It doesn't matter. Now we
see the hole is only partway through, not all the way through,
we're not concerned that something happened that we're not seeing. The other
reading of הבריא hivri which the ערוך Aruch says and רש״י also
says is that it might mean pierced through, not healed. How do
you get pierced through? I don't know, you can look at רש״י,
he quotes the source for that. אגמריה אותו בחבורא. Agmarei oto bechabura.
Anyway, whatever. He quotes a פסוק pasuk where it means to pierce
through. So anyway, you see the—you see it in the skin, you
see it in the wall, but it's not all the way through.
We're not concerned that it actually did pierce through and that it
somehow we didn't see it and it got covered up. Okay. Now
the גמרא's Gemara going to get into this discussion about how many
things are you concerned about because remember, a minute before we said
if there's a concern that an animal got clawed, we have to
check. Here we're saying if the animal has a thorn in its
esophagus, we're not concerned. Now, of course, the difference could be because
there's no way of checking and there was a way of checking
the other thing. But this is now going to be the גמרא's
Gemara question: how concerned are we about possible things that we can't
see? Okay, so let's take a look. Why don't we read the
גמרא? Gemara ולעולא מאי שנא מספק דרוסה? U-le-Ulla mai shena mi-safek dirusah?
Why is this different from the case we just said before about
the concern that an animal got clawed? קסבר עולא אין חוששין לספק
דרוסה Kasavar Ulla ein chosheshin le-safek dirusah because he says if there's
a concern the animal got clawed, fine, we don't know it, we're
not concerned. If we don't know for sure, we don't worry about
it. Again, interestingly, even though there something can be checked and here
nothing can be checked, and we know I've just been telling you
that one of the differences that we actually do make is, you
know, is that if you can check it you might have to
check it. So it could be that it's enough of a concern
that forces you to check, but if you can't check then you
just assume it's okay. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. It says
that עולא Ulla would say we're not concerned for when there's a
doubt. So the גמרא Gemara. says: ומאי שנא משתי חתיכות אחת של
חלב ואחת של שומן? Umai shena mi-shtei chatichot achat shel chelev ve-achat
shel shuman? But come on, obviously there are cases where you are
concerned when there's a doubt. If you have two pieces of food
in front of you, one is permissible fat and one is forbidden
fat, עולא Ulla is not going to say, you know, you can
just pick one randomly and eat it. Obviously you have to be
strict if you don't know. הגמרא Hagemara says: no, התם איתחזק איסורא.
Hatam itchazek issura. There—there it's established that one of them is forbidden.
You know that a forbidden thing is here, so you have to
play it safe and avoid it. Here the whole point is you
don't know that there was ever this problem in the animal. You
know there's a thorn, but you don't ever know that it actually
pierced through the wall. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומאי שנא מהשוחט
בסכין ונמצאת פגומה? Umai shena mehashochet besakin venimtzeit peguma? How about when
you שחט shacht with a knife that was checked and later you
find a nick in the knife? So there were concerned that maybe
it had a nick at the time of the שחיטה. shechita. הגמרא
Hagemara says: no, התם איתיליד ריעותא בסכין. Hatam ityelid rei'uta besakin. Yeah,
but there you do a—you see that there became a problem in
the knife and you have to be concerned maybe the problem existed
earlier. So there the question is: is this problem, if it existed
earlier, would have made the שחיטה shechita invalid? Here you never actually
see a problem, you just see a partially punctured esophagus. So the
גמרא Gemara says: ומאי שנא מספק טומאה ברשות היחיד דספיקו טמא? Umai
shena misafek tumah birshut hayachid desfeiko tamei? How about doubtful טומאה tumah
in a private domain where we say something is assumed to be
טמא? tamei? So we're always strict by doubts. And there also it's
just a question, an abstract possibility, not a concrete knowledge. So the
גמרא Gemara says: ולטעמיך דאמרינן ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור. Uleta'ameich
de-amrinan safek tumah birshut harabim sfeiko tahor. According to you, then what
about doubtful טומאה tumah in a public domain where we say we
assume it's
טהור? tahor? אלא התם הילכתא גמירי לה מסוטה. Ela hatam hilchata gemiri
la mi-Sotah. There—there it is something we learned from סוטה, Sotah, it's
an arbitrary rule about טומאה, tumah, but we don't apply it. Now
this is such a bizarre גמרא. Gemara It goes through all these
cases of here we're strict by ספק, safek here we're not strict
by ספק. I mean, you know, we should—there are some basic parameters
about when you're חושש choshesh and not. And תוספות says, and what
the גמרא Gemara. is completely forgetting here is the principle that we
said earlier, that once an animal is שחט, shachted, we assume it's
okay until you can prove that there's a טריפה. It has a
חזקה of being okay. Why isn't it introducing the concept of חזקה
here at all? Okay, but anyway what the גמרא is basically saying
is that if you have something that makes you wonder what happened,
but you don't have concrete evidence that there's a problem, you can
assume it's okay. But are you assuming it's okay because we basically
say a ספק without concrete evidence you always rule leniently, or is
it because, you know, is it because like this idea that there
was a חזקת היתר? chezkat heter? There was a presumption of being
permissible. That level of specificity, which is critical, the גמרא is not
introducing. We're basically over—let me just read one line—last line to wrap
this up. The גמרא says like this: יתיב ההוא מרבנן קמיה דרב
כהנא ויתיב וקאמר. Yativ hahu merabbanan kamey de-Rav Kahana ve-yativ ve-ka'amar. So
a rabbi was sitting before רב כהנא Rav Kahana and saying: נמצאת.
Nimtzeit. No, the thorn in the esophagus is only okay if it's
found in the esophagus but not—not pressed into the wall. Pressed into
the wall, we do have to concern that it pierced the entire
wall.
אבל יושב חיישינן. Aval yashav chayshinan. We are concerned, against the earlier
גמרא. אמר ליה רב כהנא. Amar lei Rav Kahana. So רב כהנא
Rav Kahana said: לא תציתו ליה. Lo ttzitu lei. Don't listen to
him. יושב איתמר. Yashav itamar. that it was actually in the wall
of the esophagus, and nevertheless we're not concerned that it went all
the way through. אבל נמצאת aval nimtzet but if it was just
happened to be in the esophagus, the thorn, לא איצטריכא ליה לעולא
lo itztreicha lei l'Ulla Ulla would never have even bothered needed to
tell you that it was okay. דהולכי חיוי ברייתא קוצי אכלי dehulchei
chivya baraita kotzei achli all animals of the field eat, you know,
thorns. So, of course there'll be a thorn in the actual hollow
of the esophagus. Ulla wouldn't have mentioned that. Ulla's saying even in
the wall of the esophagus it's not a problem, we are not
concerned that it goes all the way through. Okay. To be continued.
I wondered about that because it's